Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, 2005-2009: SdArch 29
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Series 2: Oral History Interviews, 2006–2009
  - 29-84: Strickler, Robert H. (Twig), interviewed by Jessica Woodward, April 23, 2007
    - Original audio-disc, April 23, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-076)
  - 29-85: Swope, Richard, interviewed by Tim Van Schaick, March 7, 2007
    Records an interview with Richard Swope, of Dayton Virginia, who discusses his experiences working in the turkey industry for over fifty years. Swope discusses his childhood on a dairy farm in Dayton; work for Wampler Company in the 1950s as a field representative; his partnership with his brother to raise turkeys under contract with Wampler; changes in turkey breeding and genetics; colony houses in the 1950s that used coal or wood heat; automated feeders and ventilation systems; building costs of confinement houses; drugs, diseases, predators, and problems with noise and rodents; tunnel vs. static ventilation; changes in demand for turkey products; turkey mortality and the disposal of dead turkeys; poultry litter and waste management; free range poultry; ethanol movement and fuel prices; horseback riding; his views of Pilgrim's Pride, the Shenandoah Valley Poultry Growers Coop (VPGC), and Cargill.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 7, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Original audio-disc, March 7, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-077)
    - Preservation master, March 7, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-099)
  - 29-86: Thomson, Forrest, interviewed by Daniel O'Keefe, November 21, 2006
    Records an interview with Forrest Thomson of Harrisonburg, Virginia, who has worked in various jobs in the poultry industry. Thomson describes his decision to study poultry science at Virginia Tech; his job at Wampler Foods as the Assistant Breeder Manager; decision to have his own breeder opation, producing eggs for Wampler Foods, Pilgrims Pride and Ag Forte; producing toms for the Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative (VPGC); work on the assembly line at Wampler Foods; automation and technology; immigration and labor; a typical day working on the assembly line at a poultry plant; OSHA and regulations, accidents, safety and health concerns; food safety and disease, including avian flu; regulations; slaughter houses and the humane treatment of animals; PETA.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 21, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Preservation master, November 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-87: VP Sales, interviewed by Matt McDonald, November 17, 2006
    Records an interview with the unnamed VP of Sales of the Shenandoah Valley Poultry Growers Cooperative, in Harrisonburg, Virginia. This person discusses their daily work in production, sales and distribution; turkey production at the plant; previous work at Pilgrim's Pride and Cargill; SVPGC decision to sell antibiotic-free, vegetarian-fed turkeys; pricing and contract models with growers and distributors; relationship with the The USA Poultry and Egg Export Council (USAPEEC); controlling processing costs; branding and markets in different regions of the country; grain prices and concern about the impact of ethanol and corn production; farm bill and agricultural subsidies; consolidation in the poultry industry, super market chains, and food services.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 17, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Original audio-disc, November 17, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-078)
    - Preservation master, November 17, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-098)
  - 29-88: Venable, Mary, interviewed by Kristen Brady, March 22, 2007
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 22, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Original audio-disc, March 22, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-079)
    - Preservation master, March 22, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-89: Venable, Mary, interviewed by Terrence Halliburton, April 24, 2007
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 24, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Original audio-disc, April 24, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-080)
    - Original audio-disc, April 24, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-081)
    - Preservation master, April 24, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-90: Vines, James and Laura, interviewed by Dottie Westhafer, March 8, 2007
    Records an interview with Jim and Laura Vines, cattle farmers and former poultry growers from Verona, Virginia. Jim Vine discusses buying a 150 acre farm in the Shenandoah Valley in 1978, and investing in infrastructure to raise poultry; working for Rocco, Inc. and his relationship with the Strickler family; his work as an electrical engineer and Virginia Electric and Power Company (VEPCO); competition within the poultry industry; decision to go to night school and continue education at JMU; stigma associated with being a turkey farmer; challenges of converting poultry houses for other use; investment in cattle and his calf-cow operation.Vines describes various aspects of the poultry business, including diseases; different breeds of toms (male turkeys); the process of packaging chicks for mail delivery; moisture content and heat in the poultry houses; feed and nutrition for poultry; and the rating scale Rocco used to rank and pay growers.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 8, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Original audio-disc, March 8, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-082)
    - Preservation master, March 8, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-91: Walker, Jacqueline B., interviewed by Sherri Lee Jones, November 27, 2007
    Records in interview with Jacqueline B. Walker, an associate professor of History at James Madison University, and her work as a turkey grader at the Marvel Poultry Plan, in Harrisonburg, Virginia Walker. Walker describes her work grading turkeys; uniform and dress; training by USDA inspectors; working on the conveyor belt; union membership; her relationships and friendships with coworkers and supervisors; her observations about social dynamics at the plant; rules at the plant; safety precautions; injuries and joint pain; the impact of higher education; a strike; her views on automation; and her views on Japanese and American approaches to manufacturing and production
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 27, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Original audio-disc, November 27, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-083)
    - Preservation master, November 27, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-92: Walker, Jacqueline B., interviewed by Matthew Neese, March 27, 2007
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 27, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Preservation master, March 27, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-93: Wampler, Charles W. Jr., interviewed by Jessica Silveri, March 15, 2007 and March 17, 2007
    Records an interview with Charles Wampler, Jr who worked for the Wampler family poultry businesses. Wampler describes his education at Dayton High School and Bridgewater College; work for the Wampler Feed and Seed company; building turkey houses; the family chicken, cattle and feed businesses; "contract growing" as a business model; different breeds of turkeys, including bronze, Holland, and white; changes in the grow-time for turkeys; poultry diseases, medications, and drugs; the transition from raising turkeys on range to raising them in confinement; vertical integration in the poultry industry; poultry litter and waste disposal; relationship with the other poultry companies; retirement in the 1970s. In a follow-up interview, Wampler discusses the Wampler Feed and Seed Company and changes in poultry nutrition; the contract model for growing turkeys; the formation of Wampler-Longacre and Wampler Foods, Inc.; sale to Pilgrim's Pride; and the Virginia State Poultry Federation.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 15, 2007 and March 17, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Original audio-disc, March 15, 2007 and March 17, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-084)
    - Original audio-disc, March 15, 2007 and March 17, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-085)
    - Preservation master, March 15, 2007 and March 17, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-94: Wampler, Charles W. Jr., interviewed by Dr. Daniel Kerr and Students of HIST-337, January 1, 2008
    - Transcript and supporting documents, January 1, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Preservation master, January 1, 2008 (Box 1)
  - 29-95: Ware, Mason and Martha, interviewed by Dottie Westhafer, April 2, 2007
    Records an interview with Mason Ware and Martha Ware, poultry growers and teachers, from Mt. Solon, Virginia. The Wares discuss growing turkeys under contract for Wampler, and later for Rocco, Inc. They describe a typical work day in their poultry operation; the disposal of dead birds; composting poultry litter; debeaking and declawing the birds; different breeds of turkey; the impact of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation and Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) on their operation; poultry diseases; the decision to grow for Rocco; changes in management at Wampler; rising feed costs; lighting, ventilation and heat in the grow houses; specifications set by the poultry companies such as Wampler and Rocco; and their soil and water supply.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 2, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Original audio-disc, April 2, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-086)
    - Preservation master, April 2, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-96: Weaver, Lefa, interviewed by Heather Crabtree, April 6, 2007
    Records an interview with Lefa Weaver, of Harrisonburg Virginia regarding her work in the poultry plants in the Shenandoah Valley. Weaver discusses growing up on a turkey farm; her aunt's labor on the farm; work for the Marvel Poultry plant; stigma about having a child while not being married; her family and grandchildren; work at a hatchery, where she burned beaks, clipped nails an vaccinated birds; and pay at Marvel.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 6, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Original audio-disc, April 6, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-087)
    - Preservation master, April 6, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-97: White, Caleb, interviewed by Stephen Coords, April 19, 2009
    Records an interview with Caleb White, a nurse aid at Western State Hospital in Staunton, Virginia. White discusses his family and childhood and his decision to join the Peace Corp, his work as a nurse aid, overtime pay, movies that portray mental illness, and his plans for the future.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 19, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Original audio-disc, April 19, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-088)
    - Preservation master, April 19, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-98: Winyan, Keya and Cheryl L. Metz, interviewed by Victoria Edward, April 11, 2009
    Records an interview with Keya Winyan of Harrisonburg, Virginia. Winyan discusses her father, a descendeant of the Elm Clan of the Tuscarora Tribe of the Iroqoquis Nation, and her mother, who is of Cherokee descent. Winyan describes her life experiences, including topics such as experiences with the Baptist church; her name and its meaning; changing ceremonies; ideas about Christian and Native American spirituality; her relationship with her grandparents; her time in the Navy; getting a Masters degree in American and British Literature; her work as a stortyteller and teacher, specifically animal medicine teaching; tribal sovereignty; Leonard Peltier; discrimination and stereotyping; plutonium and uranium poisoning in the Cheyenne River; powwows; federal recognition of tribes; the Dawes Records and the Racial Integrity Act of 1924; casinos; white buffalo calf; eugenics laws in Virginia; the American Indian movement; and the story of "Jumping Mouse."
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 11, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Original audio-disc, April 11, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-089)
    - Preservation master, April 11, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-099)
  - 29-99: Wood, Karenne, interviewed by Victoria Edwards, March 3, 2009
    Records an interview with Karenne Wood of Charlottesville, Virginia, who discusses her life and work as the Program Director of the Virginia Indian Heritage Program. Wood describes her work in linguistic anthropologist, studying the Monacan language, Tutelo; her family; addresses stereotypes of Native peoples; her work with the Siouxon language; Cherokee in Virginia; media portrayal of Native people; Virginia Standard of Learning in Social Sciences as it relates to Native Peoples; the American Indian Movement; desegregation of schools; Virginia Council on Indians; and the Racial Integrity Act of 1924.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 3, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Original audio-disc, March 3, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-090)
    - Preservation master, March 3, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)